COMMENTARY:
The Fly came to me...
...from Mel Brooks, the producer.
He was working with Stuart Cornfeld.
And it was a script
that I had seen before...
...and was interested in somewhat,
but was very distracted...
...because I was working on
Total Recall with Dino De Laurentiis.
And I just wanna say
that this credit...
...this title moment...
...the sort of fluttering
of the words "The Fly"...
...was something I saw in a teaser trailer
that was done to promote the film.
And I liked it so much, I decided to
incorporate it into the head credits...
...because it wasn't something
we had initially thought of doing.
But the script for The Fly that I read
had been written by Chuck Pogue.
And it had a really wonderful rethinking
of the original movie...
...the Vincent Price movie.
The DNA rethink...
...of why a man could turn into
a sort of half-fly...
...and the sequence of physical events
that led up to it...
...were very brilliantly rethought
by Chuck Pogue.
But I wasn't very happy
with the characters...
...and I think they were
a little bit too close, in a way...
...to the characters in the original
short story by George Langelaan...
...who was, I think, a Belgian writer...
...whose story was published
in Playboy in 1957 ...
...and republished many times
after that. A very popular story.
So my contribution
to the rewriting of the script...
...was basically the characters
and the dialogue.
Which sounds like a lot, but it
wasn't everything. There was a lot...
...that attracted me to Chuck's script.
And felt, in fact, so much like me
that I was kind of surprised.
I'd have never-- I'd never really seen
a script that had so many things in it...
...that felt like me to me.
So I was very interested
to see where it would lead...
...and it led to Jeff Goldblum...
...and the woman that was his girlfriend
at the time, Geena Davis.
I auditioned a lot of actresses
for the role.
And I felt that because
Jeff's presence as Seth Brundle...
...the eccentricity, the charisma...
...and not to mention the fact
that Jeff is very tall, about 6'5"...
...really wanted to find an actress who
would match him in all of those ways.
And it seemed like kismet
that he should be...
His girlfriend should be Geena.
And it took a while before we came
around to saying to ourselves...
...and I mean me and Jeff, "Should we
consider Geena Davis to play this role?"
She'd mostly done comedies.
And the idea of a woman
who was tall, beautiful, sexy...
...and also very funny and eccentric,
well, that really attracted me.
And I felt that she was
a perfect match for Jeff.
VERONICA:
You're not a very good drunk.
COMMENTARY:
The problem, really...
...in working with a couple
who were so close...
...and had been together for
quite some time, was that Geena...
...who is an adept mimic...
...she basically would do Jeff.
I mean, she was like Jeff
in her linguistic rhythm...
...her speech rhythms
and her body language.
Because Jeff has a very strange...
...kind of infectious way
of speaking and moving.
And Geena was like his sister...
...more than a lover
that he'd just met.
And one of the things that we had to do
was to disconnect Geena from Jeff...
...for the sake of the movie...
...in terms of just her presence,
and her speech rhythms and so on.
I remember, she said, "Oh."
I said, "Geena, you're doing Jeff.
You're saying that line
the way Jeff would say it."
She said, "Oh, right. Do it
the Geena way, not the Jeff way."
And that's the kind of fun
that we had on the set. And it was fun.
Jeff, as you can see...
...is a very adept
piano player and singer.
And shortly after this shot, Jeff and
Geena did a duet for the crew together...
...with Jeff playing, and they sang
beautifully together. So it was a--
I could see where the togetherness
would come in their relationship.
But we had to make it fresh. We had to
separate them at the beginning...
...so that there was a seduction.
A mutual seduction.
And only gradually
towards the end of the movie...
...allowed them to become closer.
The telepod, and there it is
in all its glory...
Well, the first designs looked kind
of like glass showers, you know.
They were just-- Or telephone booths.
And as they were, in a way,
in the original movie of The Fly.
And I found that kind of,
hm, boring. And...
But we couldn't come up with what
the look for the telepods should be...
...until I opened my garage door
and showed my production designer...
...Carol Spier, my Ducati
single-cylinder motorcycle...
...a 450 Desmo.
And I said, "You know,
it should be more machine-y.
It should have cooling fins, for example.
It should have camshafts or something."
And I thought, "Well, let me show you."
Well, in about two minutes...
...she and her crew had taken
the engine out of my motorcycle...
...which was a vintage
Ducati single-cylinder bike...
...and taken it off to their own lab...
...where they re-created it
in a giant scale, turned it upside down.
But basically, all "Ducatisti,"
Ducati enthusiasts...
...of that particular
Italian motorcycle...
...recognized the telepod
as a Ducati cylinder head.
More than a cylinder head, it's
actually the whole cylinder structure.
So that was--
That's the basis of that design.
Italian design.
You can't beat it, it's great.
Geena, of course, and Jeff
knew very well how to play together.
Flirt and to--
Just the sexual innuendos and so on.
And Jeff, I couldn't believe my luck
when I found him for this role...
...because he had that unique
combination of geekiness...
...with believable,
credible intelligence...
...and yet the potential to become an
incredibly physical, athletic presence...
...which the role required, and which
we'll certainly see more of later.
So this is-- To me, this was a marriage
made in heaven, between me and Jeff.
That was our fusion. We were
really fusing like Brundlefly...
...because you know, I really--
When you write a script
and you are directing a movie...
...there's a sense in which a director
fuses with his leading actors.
Not just the actor,
but the actress as well.
You sort of become them.
You have to become them.
You get-- You really become attuned
to the rhythms and so on.
And it continues on past
the shooting of the movie.
It continues into the editing,
when the actor's long gone.
You're still dealing with that actor's
verbal rhythms and physical rhythms...
...and so on, because you're trying to
make them work in an editing way.
You really get into the nervous system
of your actors when you're directing.
And it is like a fusion,
a sort of Brundlefly fusion.
VERONICA:
If I had a Rolex.
You're missing the point.
Look.
Teleportation?
COMMENTARY:
The original story of "The Fly"...
...was not really a great story...
...in the sense of the quality
of its writing and so on.
I mean, Mangelaan is-- Or Langelaan
is not really a very well-known writer...
...except for that short story.
But it did have that basic concept
that is so stunning and so...
I guess you would call it
high-concept now.
It wasn't when he wrote it, obviously.
But for a little story, for a sort
of awkwardly written little story...
...it certainly had a huge impact
when it came out...
...and spawned, and that's
the right word, quite a few movies...
...and will probably spawn
a few more before it's done.
VERONICA:
What happened?
You get it but you can't handle it.
Um, your stocking...
COMMENTARY: The name "Brundle"
I took from a Formula One racer...
...and a car racer
named Martin Brundle.
A lot of the names
that I invent for my characters...
...come from the annals
of motor racing.
I don't know why.
Just for some reason.
I'm a big enthusiast of motor racing.
And even though Brundle...
...as he's already explained,
gets motion sick.
And that's one of the reasons
that he's invented teleportation...
...is that he won't have to
get into a vehicle.
VERONICA:
How could you do this alone?
I don't work alone.
There's stuff in there I don't
understand. I'm really...
...a systems manager.
I farm out...
COMMENTARY: The idea of having
Seth's home and lab...
...in one place, in a warehouse,
in a kind of loft space...
...seems obvious now,
and you've seen it a million times...
...and we've seen a million movies
in which people...
...live in lofts and warehouses
and so on...
...but at the time,
it was really rather unusual.
There weren't too many movies
before The Fly...
...in which the lead character
lived in his workspace...
...and that that workspace was a kind of
old-- A semi-abandoned warehouse.
BRUNDLE:
What's that?
COMMENTARY:
And, of course, it worked perfectly...
...for the theatricality of the piece.
I've often said that The Fly
could be a play...
...and in fact, I'm working right now
with Howard Shore...
...on an opera version of The Fly.
Because it's really-- It's almost--
We knew from the very beginning...
...that there was a theatricality
and an operatic aspect to the movie.
That it was not-- Even though
it's very-- A very small cast...
...it really is basically three
characters in one space.
Four, if you count the baboon.
VERONICA: But you told it to me.
-I suppose I did but--
-Sure did.
-Now wait a minute.
COMMENTARY: So it's not an epic,
but it's more intimate than that.
But there is an operatic element to it.
And that's what we went for
with the music.
It's not exactly over-the-top,
but it doesn't restrain itself either.
And I have to say that my response
to seeing this movie...
...after not having seen it
since 1986 or 7...
...in order to do this commentary...
...I was really struck by
how disturbing a film it is, I have to say.
And how emotional it is.
Certainly, that was something
that attracted people to it...
...who normally would not be
interested in a horror film...
...especially one that
gets relatively gory.
There were always--
There was always a lot of...
...positive response to the love story,
to the triangle you see here...
...with John Getz,
playing Stathis Borans.
And it was something that, I guess at
a certain point after making the movie...
...I kind of lost track of myself.
And it struck me
on seeing it just recently...
...how right the people were
who had that reaction...
...and how disturbing
and emotional the film is.
It really does work as a love story.
John Getz, I saw him in Blood Simple,
the Coen brothers film.
And I loved what he had done
in that movie...
...and was very excited
to get him for this.
Just the presence, the voice,
the arrogance...
...but also the vulnerability
and the sarcasm and so on...
...mean,
which this character required.
Someone who could really
stand up to Jeff's strength...
...with his own
different kind of strength.
BRUNDLE:
You didn't waste time.
I'm not getting any younger.
He wasn't impressed by your tape?
He thinks you're a con man.
COMMENTARY:
This is, I think...
...the only version of The Fly
that had a love affair...
...that developed before your eyes.
Both the short story and the early film...
...and Chuck Pogue's original script...
...had the scientist married
when we meet him.
And so it was a sort of
a more domestic...
...established marital situation
at the beginning.
I really wanted
there to be more of a process...
...more of the excitement
of a seduction...
...and a love affair developing.
And I wanted Brundle to be
very articulate about what he does...
...because I wanted him
to be very articulate...
...about what was happening to him
as the film progressed.
And in other versions of The Fly...
...including the script
that I originally read...
...the scientist loses his voice
very early on...
...relatively early on in the movie,
as he transforms.
And therefore is limited...
...in terms of what he can express,
how articulate he can be.
And I think in the original movie...
...he can only type some words
on an old typewriter...
...and only, of course, with one hand.
So I wanted to hear what Brundle's
experience of transformation was.
I wanted him to be articulate about it.
And so that's one of the, I think...
...more subtle but really
more important changes...
...that I made to the way that his
disease, his transformation, progresses.
BRUNDLE:
What do you have so far?
Enough to make you nervous.
Why not get more? Make me
your major project, a book.
Not a magazine article.
Follow me and my work,
day by day in detail.
I have no life, so there's nothing
for you to interfere with.
COMMENTARY:
The idea of embedded journalists...
...I had it right here, literally,
with this couple.
The idea of a journalist actually
becoming the lover of her subject.
You can't get more embedded
than that.
BRUNDLE:
--frontiers, of time and space."
The book will end with me...
...transporting myself
from one telepod to another.
That's what's missing.
Wait for me that long?
COMMENTARY:
The design of this apartment--
This is a set, of course.
And it's a kind of a classic
Toronto apartment look.
The movie,
without making a big deal out of it...
...really does take place in Toronto,
as most of my movies do.
I just feel very
at home and comfortable...
...and as though
I really know what I'm doing.
I'm not really looking for the exotic.
I'm really looking to--
For grounding and for depth...
...rather than doing
an exotic, epic-type movie.
Although I guess M. Butterfly
had a bit of that in it.
This moment coming up,
a classic moment in cinema, I think...
...came out of just fooling around
before we did the take.
Geena flushed the toilet. As a joke.
Because everybody knows,
who's lived in an apartment like this...
...that when you flush the toilet,
the cold water goes into the toilet...
...and the shower becomes hot.
And so that was--
We were just fooling around,
as we often do.
And came up with a nice moment.
VERONICA: Yeah?
-Yeah.
That's because unconsciously...
COMMENTARY:
One of the surprises for me...
...after sort of a rediscovery
in watching the movie...
...was how strong John Getz's
performance is. How subtle it is.
Because you know he is an asshole...
...he is obnoxious.
But he does become heroic,
and he becomes vulnerable...
...and you begin to realize...
...that his love for Veronica...
...is as deep as Seth's.
And maybe more so, because he's
known her longer and in more detail.
So there's a complex relationship
between the two of them.
Which, once again, I kind of
had forgotten about...
...just thinking about
the movie casually.
It's one of the things
that I really liked rediscovering...
...when I watched the movie again.
VERONICA:
--Psychology Today gig.
That's not like you.
Are you getting out or am I?
I'll go. Shall I return later
and tuck you in?
No. Key.
COMMENTARY:
And I really like...
...the late-afternoon
lighting in this scene...
...sort of with the orange tint
of a low sun on one side...
...and the blue on the other.
BRUNDLE:
Initiate in five seconds.
COMMENTARY:
I really wanted the computer...
...to be voice-activated...
...because it leads to some interesting
moments later in the film.
Now, this shot
is a motion-control shot.
It was the first motion-control shot
I ever did...
...and it was in the early days
of motion control, when the...
In order to make the baboon
disappear in a moving shot...
...a shot that's traveling,
we needed to do two shots.
One with the baboon in the telepod
and one with it not in the telepod.
And in order to do that, you have
to do two shots exactly the same.
And in order to do that, you have to use
computers to control the camera.
And we had tracks of the...
The dolly traveled on a geared track.
And it was huge. I mean,
the tracks were like railroad tracks...
...for some 19th-century
steam locomotive.
They were huge, and very solid. And the
whole idea is that they should not move.
The movement has to be
replicated twice, exactly...
...80 that you can dissolve from one shot
to the other without it being obvious...
...and make the baboon disappear.
I had done quite a few
motion-control shots later...
...and the technology got smaller,
lighter and more nimble...
...every time you went to do it.
But that was a huge apparatus
to do those kind of shots.
BRUNDLE:
"Fuck" is what I'm thinking!
VERONICA:
Good.
The world will want to know that.
COMMENTARY:
Once again, the whole emotional push...
...for me for the film...
...was that Seth be articulate
about what he's feeling.
And so here we see it developed...
...in terms of the relationship between
himself and his lover journalist.
She pushes him to articulate,
to not keep it inside...
...the emotional response to things.
And then later, he does it on his own
when he becomes the Brundlefly.
I needed to have words from him
all the time.
BRUNDLE:
I don't want to talk now.
COMMENTARY: Of course, this movie,
almost 20 years ago...
...it was still at the beginning
of the sort of:
"Let's tape everything that we do.
Let's tape everything that happens.”
Of course, that's developed enormously
since then...
...with the addition of
posting your videos on the Internet.
But the anticipation
that everybody is his own journalist...
...everybody is doing a documentary
of his own life...
...was implicit in what goes on
in this movie.
VERONICA:
Five sets of exactly the same clothes?
Learned it from Einstein.
This way I don't have to...
COMMENTARY:
And yes, I did get this scene...
...from what I heard about Einstein.
That he would have identical clothes,
suits of clothes...
...so that he wouldn't
have to make choices...
...wouldn't have to
waste brainpower...
...making choices about what
he was gonna wear that day.
I've done the same myself since.
I think in my case it's just laziness.
BRUNDLE:
No, we don't have to go there.
You're very cute. You know that?
Am I?
COMMENTARY:
Well, this is my version...
...of the sexual awakening of a nerd,
I suppose.
And it has other implications...
...both metaphorical and emotional
for the movie.
Because Brundle ends up going through
quite a few different kinds of changes...
...in this movie,
not just the sci-fi change.
But I wanted him to have a bunch
of changes going on in his life...
...at the same time,
and that they're all interlocked.
Ouch, this does look painful,
doesn't it?
BRUNDLE:
Ow.
Sorry.
Oh. Huh.
I wondered what happened to this.
-Do you have any disinfectant?
-No, that's okay.
I'll kiss it for you.
COMMENTARY:
This is the--
So far the only movie
that I've ever directed...
...during which the shooting of which
I have not gained weight.
We were very much into
working out on this movie.
And as I say, you know,
when you fuse with your leading actor...
...and your leading actor
is pumping up...
...with weights, with dumbbells,
before every shot...
...where he doesn't have
a lot of clothes on...
...then there's a trickle-down effect,
you know.
And so I was working out
in my trailer, in my office...
...between shots, between takes.
And, of course, Jeff
was doing the same thing.
So I actually ended up being in
quite good shape after this movie...
...unlike most other movies
where I gain 15 or 20--
As much as 20 pounds,
as I did on M. Butterfly.
We will see more
of Jeff's muscularity later.
It actually plays
an important part in the narrative.
And then this is another
motion-control shot, of course.
And the idea that a scientist
should have some poetry in his soul...
...is not at all far-fetched.
Many, many physics scientists...
...are wonderful pianists, for example.
There's something about a certain kind
of branch of science and music...
...that goes together.
Particularly, they tend to like Bach a lot.
There's a mathematical element
to the music of Bach...
...which is very seductive and engaging
for physics scientists.
VERONICA:
A monkey just came apart in there.
COMMENTARY:
But, really, brilliant scientists...
...and brilliant artists...
...there is a huge crossover in terms of
the way their creativity works.
The way they imagine things,
the way they dream solutions.
BRUNDLE:
Mm-hm.
What have we proved?
COMMENTARY:
Many famous scientists...
...have done extreme things...
...that we normally associate
with artists.
That they isolate themselves...
...that in order to come up
with a solution to a problem...
...they go to some island
off the coast of Iceland...
...and rappel down glaciers...
...and suffer physical discomfort
in order to--
Just to jar their minds
out of the rut that they're in...
...in order to come up with
different solutions and so on.
And also seeking inspiration
in poetry and painting...
...and other kinds of art.
So there's a huge element of that
in this movie...
...in terms of my understanding
of the way science works...
...and the way
the scientific mind works.
So you can be a science geek
or a science nerd...
...but it doesn't mean...
...that you have no poetry
in your soul or body.
I've set a lot of scenes in abandoned
warehouses and barns and so on.
There's something about that
that just appeals to me.
The rethinking
of the use of a structure...
...has always been something
that excited me...
...architecturally and dramatically.
But here we begin to see...
...that Stathis Borans is, in fact...
...very serious in his own crazy way...
...about his relationship with Ronnie.
He's not really about to give her up.
And she really has damaged his life
by leaving him.
To the extent that he is willing to
humiliate himself in public...
...just to make his point to her
that he's not gonna go away.
STATHIS:
For your Time Magazine cover...
...you have to look good, right?
Don't you get it?
I am finally onto something big.
-Huge.
-Yeah? What? His cock?
Crude, Stathis. Very crude.
You're too perfect.
You're a goddess.
Thanks for making my
paranoid fantasies come true.
I don't have to report to you,
you creep.
Ronnie?
You have to talk to me.
No, I don't! We're finished.
I'll spend the night
anywhere I damn well please.
Sorry. I'll take this too.
COMMENTARY:
Well, the baboon...
...was a major cast member,
I have to say.
And had quite a presence.
Baboons are quite scary.
They're very strong,
they're very volatile.
There's no such thing as a tame baboon,
that's for sure.
And, in fact, the baboon kind of fell
in love...
...with our script supervisor...
...a woman who was not very tall.
Kind of his height.
And that was a bit of a problem.
He was very attracted to her.
And Jeff, because he was much bigger
and stronger than the baboon...
...was able to dominate him.
And the baboon's wrangler, as we say--
Not really a trainer, but a wrangler,
somebody who looks after the animal.
--Said it was a good thing
that the baboon...
...formed that relationship with Jeff,
that he was subservient.
That he accepted Jeff as the sort of
alpha male who dominated him.
Otherwise, there could have been big
trouble on the set with that baboon...
...and some of the female members
of the crew.
VERONICA: Well, I was thinking that
we could take a holiday.
COMMENTARY:
I did a photo with the baboon...
...where I was kind of--
We were kind of kissing each other. But
I was well aware that at any moment...
...he might try to rip my face off,
and could probably do it quite easily.
He was scary, but beautiful.
And performed very well.
BRUNDLE:
Is this a romance we're having?
Yeah. Could be a romance.
Come here.
I have a great idea.
You like Chinese food?
Yes.
We'll have a romantic dinner here.
COMMENTARY:
I love the kind of invention...
...that goes on
sort of as a subtext in a movie...
...and the invention of Particle Magazine
was something I really enjoyed.
And this cover art.
BRUNDLE:
Yeah, I'll wait.
What's that?
[VERONICA SIGHS]
COMMENTARY:
The idea that you might have...
...a People magazine
or a TIME magazine...
...but for physics, for advanced physics.
I kind of enjoyed that idea.
I'm not sure that it exists.
I guess Scientific American
is the closest that comes.
It's hard to believe this movie
was made 20 years ago...
...until you see phones like that.
Then you are aware
of how things have changed.
VERONICA:
I have to scrape it off my shoe...
...and get rid of it, once and for all.
Hi.
[DOOR CLOSES]
COMMENTARY:
This movie was made before--
Really before there was CGI.
Everything in this movie was done
on an optical bench, not in a computer.
No frames of this film
went in and out of computers...
...and that's almost unthinkable these
days, especially for a sci-fi movie.
But it was all done the old way,
the handmade way.
The Seth Brundle way, I guess.
VERONICA:
You told me there was no story.
You said Brundle was a con man.
I've decided to trust
your journalistic instincts.
Thanks very much.
But this is not your story.
It's mine.
Says who?
I sent you to the Bartok party
to see what you could find.
Your discovery is my discovery.
I have a lot of background on Brundle.
COMMENTARY:
I guess this would be a sort of...
...sexual-harassment-in-the-workplace
situation now.
The employer and the employee.
I think that was in the air,
even in 1986.
But it wasn't as...
Had not been as codified...
...and as embedded in law and so on
as it has been since then.
STATHIS: Look, just keep me informed.
All right?
As a friend?
As a professional confidante?
That's all?
I don't want you
to disappear from my life.
COMMENTARY:
But here he says something...
...that's meant to be
true and touching.
Underneath all the sort of--
The bullying and the arrogance...
...Is a man who is desperate to keep
this woman in his life any way he can.
And he really cares
for her and about her.
They do have a past together.
VERONICA:
As always.
Couldn't disappoint you.
Residue means your old boyfriend,
doesn't it?
COMMENTARY:
And here's another relationship.
Seth and his baboon, of course.
BRUNDLE:
"From the desk of Stathis Borans."
How about, "Under the desk
of Stathis Borans"?
COMMENTARY: Now, given that
you can't really train a baboon...
...this is not an animal
that will do tricks for you.
We had to find ways
to get him to perform.
And...
In this case,
we actually attached a living fly...
...to, in essence, a tiny fishing line...
...made out of-- I think it was
filament from light bulbs.
So that was basically invisible,
because, as I say, in those days...
...you couldn't remove
a line or a wire...
...by going into a computer. You would
have to hand-paint it out, every frame.
You couldn't do it in a computer.
So we had to sort of
play that fly, literally, on a...
With a fishing rod
around the nose of the baboon...
...so that he could respond to the fly.
And that was our
first moment where...
...a fly, any fly, makes his appearance.
Of course, he becomes a star now.
The telepod ended up
traveling around the world, actually...
...to various exhibits of props
from my movies.
It went to Tokyo.
It went to Thessalonica...
...in Greece. It went to Paris.
And it was at the Royal Ontario Museum
in Toronto, as well.
It had to keep being rebuilt because, of
course, props are never built to last.
There's no reason to make them last.
And so they're usually not...
...sealed against the weather
and so on.
And this telepod ended up
in Carol Spier's backyard, decaying...
...until suddenly it was refurbished
and sent off to Paris.
A new life.
A transformation, in fact.
Now, here we begin to get into
the physicality of Seth.
A nerd, a geek with muscles.
And a very athletic body.
BRUNDLE:
Now, you tell me.
Am I different somehow?
"Is it live or is it Memorex?"
COMMENTARY:
And there's the baboon mugging...
...giving me-- Giving me some--
Good look towards the camera.
This hallway was on a location.
And then the interior was a set
that we controlled.
And then we built a bit of the hallway
so that when we opened the door...
...you could see it.
But now we're, of course, on our set.
So unlike the original movie
of The Fly...
...he comes through
the teleportation...
. first of all...
...out of love and frustration and
drunkenness, not just scientific curiosity.
So there's an emotional element there
that there wasn't quite in the original.
And then also...
...we are surprised to see that he seems
to not be transformed at all.
He's not changed. His head is
not a giant fly's head. And his...
One of his hands
is not a giant fly claw.
It always bugged me,
if I can make the pun...
...that, in the original,
the fly's head...
...was human-sized, or actually fit
over a human's head, of course.
Because there was no scientific
or logical reason why...
...if the head swap happened, that
the fly's head should suddenly be bigger.
I didn't-- There was no rationale for that
that worked for me.
There was no way to make that--
And even as a kid,
seeing the movie in 1957, which I did--
And it had a big impact, of course,
when it came out, that movie.
Even though I think its campiness
and its flaws and on certain levels...
...were obvious even then to a kid.
That bothered me. There were two
things that bothered me.
One was the proportions
of the fly head.
There was no way it could be big
instead of just fly-sized.
And the second thing was
there was a famous shot...
...that's the fly's point of view.
And it was a mosaic.
It was identical shots of his wife.
You know, sort of a hundred of them.
The fly looking at his screaming wife.
We all know that insect eyes
have facets...
...unlike human eyes. Many facets,
hundreds of them, thousands of them.
But that was also wrong.
Because as a junior entomologist,
as I was at the time...
...I knew that that's not
the way flies saw.
The idea is that there's no functional
value to a repetition of the same image.
That doesn't help an insect at all,
like a dragonfly...
...for example,
which has almost 360-degree eyes.
Each one of those little facets
would be a different...
...piece of a puzzle of a big picture.
So it was wrong.
It was scientifically wrong.
And it didn't make any sense.
And that bugged me too as a kid.
I was determined that we would not
make those kind of mistakes.
That there would be no kids like me
watching my version of The Fly...
...who would say, "Yeah, but that's
not the way insects" whatever.
Well, because of
Chuck Pogue's rethinking...
...of the sort of the DNA situation...
...which, of course,
was not known in 1957--
DNA was not...
Had only really just begun
to be understood at that time...
...and not really by the general public.
So the rethinking of the movie
as being a gradual transformation...
...because of the fusing
of the DNA of the fly...
...and the DNA of Brundle
meant that I could avoid...
...automatically would avoid...
...sort of the crude errors that--
As I thought of them
when I saw the original Fly.
And the original Fly was--
The movie...
...was set in Montreal,
for some reason.
And the characters all had French names.
It was quite odd.
They weren't French-Canadian names.
They didn't have French-Canadian
accents. They had French accents...
...which-- Anybody who knows Quebec
knows that...
...those are two different kinds
of accents.
So for a Canadian watching the original
Fly, there were a lot of oddities.
I don't know how it appeared to
Americans or to anyone else...
...but it certainly seemed wrong
in a strange way. In that strange way.
Now, Jeff...
...who, as I say, is about 6'5"...
...could do the beginnings
of these gymnastic moves.
And he was very impressive
to the gymnasts...
...who we brought in
to do the rest of the move.
Now, this is a gymnast
who's about 5'8" doing that.
But, of course, that's Jeff right there.
Gymnasts are not 6'5".
The proportions of muscles to height
and so on dictate that...
...most gold-medal-winning gymnasts
are about 54", 5'6", 5'6" at maximum.
We found a couple of gymnasts
who were more like 5'8"...
...and they were considered huge
in terms of competing gymnasts.
But they were nonetheless
very impressed...
...with the moves that Jeff could do,
which of course helped me...
...because the fact that he could do the
beginnings of these moves on his own...
...helped with the illusion
of these stunt--
Well, they're actually
competing gymnasts...
...standing in for Jeff.
It takes years of training to be able
to do these things.
And also, since it's a movie...
...I had them do it over and over
and over again...
...to the point where they were starting
to not be able to do the moves.
And, of course, they say,
"You know, when we do competitions...
...you're basically training for months
and years, and you do it once."
You know, you do your routine once,
when you do the competition.
You don't do it over and over.
You don't do take 12.
So I burned through a couple
of gymnasts getting the routine down.
And I wanted it not to just be...
...strength moves, not just being able
to lift heavy weights and so on, which I--
I wanted him to show agility...
...because flies are fantastic fliers.
And, of course, I couldn't have Jeff
flying around.
So to me the alternative was...
...that he should become incredibly
strong in proportion to his body...
...as insects are...
...and that he should be
nimble and agile...
...as flies are,
in terms of the way they fly.
This sequence was shot...
...in the Kensington Market
section of Toronto.
That gentleman in the tuque
was our props master on the movie.
You're constantly bribing your crew
with little cameos.
And it's probably
the most traditional love affair...
...that I've ever depicted in any
of my movies, this part right here.
But, of course, we know
that under the surface...
...strange things are happening.
And here's the first indication--
BRUNDLE: --about what
I'm feeling and why. I'm thinking...
COMMENTARY: --of the bad part
of what might be happening.
BRUNDLE:
--and reassembled--
It's like filtering coffee.
COMMENTARY: Because after all,
flies are speedy, aren't they?
And Jeff is very speedy in this scene.
The idea of fly DNA
as an amphetamine was part of...
...what I liked about the rethinking...
...of the original transformation...
...which was...
...quite physical,
quite straightforward, really.
BRUNDLE:
Interestingly, when I achieved...
...what will prove to be my
life's work...
...I've become the real me, finally.
So, listen...
COMMENTARY:
We added some dialogue to this scene...
...Jeff and I. Just...
So that Jeff could have more
to accelerate with...
...and go further than what I had
originally written for him.
He wrote a little bit of
the ending of this... Of this sequence.
BRUNDLE:
It makes a man a king.
Since I left the pod, I feel great.
COMMENTARY: I suppose,
it being the '80s, you could also...
...think of the cocaine effect.
This is very much a kind of
cocaine exuberance.
Feeling of omnipotence and so on.
And I really did want there to be
a strangely attractive...
...though dangerous upside to
the fly fusion, which of course...
...in the original story, in the original
movie, there's nothing like that.
Obviously, having your head
switched for a fly's...
...and not being able to talk...
...there's no real upside to that,
I suppose, except for Halloween.
So the idea of sexual potency...
...and mental agility
and physical strength...
...all of these things can be yours
if you go through the telepod with a fly.
And because there's a strange--
I think it's just more interesting and
more complex and more like real life...
...if there is...
...a strange attraction
or seductiveness...
...to the hideous thing
that's happening to you.
Everybody--
A disease does transform people.
And humans being humans,
they often try to find...
...a positive element
in what's happening to them...
...even though they wish
it weren't happening to them.
So I was trying to do that narratively,
to give that same structure...
...that for Brundle at the moment,
he's not really in denial.
He's just in total acceptance, really,
of what's happened to him.
And, of course,
he's gonna wanna share it.
And that's also a structure,
a narrative trope...
...a twist that you couldn't have
if it were only a negative thing.
In the original movie,
there was no question...
...of the scientist wanting his wife
to experience what he had experienced.
But here, we do have that.
Because it's still a relationship,
it's still an ongoing relationship.
So this is another complication...
...another emotional,
visceral complication...
...that I was excited to discover when
I was writing this part of the script.
VERONICA:
Don't give me that...
...born-again teleportation. I'm scared.
What do I have to say?
I'm not gonna do it!
You're a fucking drag, you know?
COMMENTARY: And Howard's music
is terrific in this sequence.
It swirls and it...
It's a musical equivalent of the dialogue,
really, and the emotion.
It's not just a sort of
accentuating of it.
But it's a sort of an addition to it
and another level of it.
It's quite extraordinary, I think.
BRUNDLE:
--destroyed and re-created.
Think you woke me up about the flesh?
You only know society's
straight line about the flesh.
You can't penetrate society's
sick gray fear of the flesh.
COMMENTARY:
And once again...
...the fact that Brundle can be articulate
about what's going on in him...
...even when he's being quite crazed
with it, was important to me.
I really wanted that.
I didn't want a mute.
By this time in the original,
the scientist would not be able to speak.
To me, that took away too many
of my dramatic weapons to do that.
And here, I remember Mel Brooks,
when we were doing the music...
...when we were recording
the music in London, he said:
"Is this music too much? I mean,
the guy's just walking down the street."
And I said, "No, Mel, the guy is about
to meet his destiny."
He said, "Oh, okay. Yeah.
Then it's okay."
We knew it was operatic,
but it was meant to be.
And we weren't holding back.
Now, if you listen, I think
in the background of this song...
...you are going to hear...
...a song called "Help Me"...
...which Nile Rodgers, a very well-known
music producer, produced.
At one point...
...there was a question
of having a song in the movie...
...that we could then make a video of,
because that was held to be...
...a good way of promoting a movie.
And...
...a song was written.
We'll get back to that.
This man is George Chuvalo...
...who was the Canadian heavyweight
boxing champion for many years...
...who fought Muhammad Ali and
George Foreman and everybody else...
...and was never,
ever knocked off his feet, ever.
Not by anybody.
George is just
a total sweetheart of a guy...
...and has the greatest
boxing stories to tell.
And I'm a boxing fan.
And the idea that we could get George
to do this scene...
...was very exciting to me, I have to say.
I had a lot of fun with him.
He had acted before.
This was not his first.
And his forearm,
which features large in this scene...
...it was about as big as my thigh,
I have to say.
He's a big guy.
And strong as Jeff is, there's no way
that he would really win...
...this arm-wrestling competition
without a little help...
...from our special-effects guys.
You need fly juice to do this.
And you need major special effects
there, of the on-set kind.
We, of course, did a cast
of George's forearm...
...to make that
fake forearm and hand.
And I swear it was as big
as my thigh.
TAWNY:
Are you a bodybuilder?
BRUNDLE: I build bodies. I take them
apart and put them back together.
TAWNY:
Well, you sure took Marky apart.
-Let's go to my place.
-Your place?
Well, okay.
I live with my mother anyway.
COMMENTARY:
Well, the song that was developed...
...for the movie, called "Help Me"...
...was, in fact, I thought,
quite a good song.
Quite a good rock 'n' roll song.
But as I pointed out,
it really didn't fit into the movie.
And I had to show Mel and Stuart
that even using it...
...for the end credits was a disaster...
...because the music was so strong
and emotional and so operatic...
...that to suddenly throw
a rock song in, however good...
...would just bring the whole movie
down completely.
And...
...they argued for it until I played it
for them in London, and then they said:
"You know, you're completely right."
So it ended up as a kind of
almost just barely hearable...
...background sound in the bar scene.
But, as I say,
I always really did like the--
I really did like the song. It's a good
song, but it sort of disappeared.
TAWNY:
Whoa.
COMMENTARY:
And once again...
...Jeff's physical strength and stamina
helped enormously.
I didn't have to do effects
in this scene.
I mean, I did have a stuntman
do some of the running...
...carrying the actress up the stairs.
But Jeff, as you could see,
did quite a lot of it.
And we had to do quite a few takes,
and, believe me, that is hard to do.
And Jeff was up to it. His physicality
was a huge asset to the movie.
Most of the roles he plays,
I guess that isn't the case.
But this role was a very physical role.
TAWNY:
Wow.
COMMENTARY:
And Jeff was not shy.
I mean, Jeff was not--
You know, there was no false modesty
or anything about Jeff.
I mean, he would've done this scene
completely naked if I had asked him to.
It wasn't a problem for him.
I didn't wanna distract from the movie
by doing that, so we didn't do that.
Well, in that look of Jeff's,
you see the whole physicality...
...the danger and everything implicit
in the transformation into the fly.
It was a great, great look.
Great dramatic moment.
BRUNDLE:
It's your turn.
-To do what?
-To go through.
No. I don't want to try that.
It'll make you feel sexy.
I already feel sexy.
How about...
COMMENTARY:
Flies don't like alcohol.
Insects don't drink alcohol.
Actually, probably somewhere
in the world...
...there is one that does,
because they're so adaptable.
It's just one of their strengths.
But, certainly, flies don't like it.
And here, of course,
we have a moment that ended up...
...being the tag line
for the whole movie, which was:
VERONICA:
Be afraid. Be very afraid.
COMMENTARY:
"Be afraid. Be very afraid."
And that really came from Mel.
Because we were talking
about this scene...
...and he said to me,
"No, I think she should say--
Because she should be afraid.
She should be very afraid."
I said, "Mel, I really like that.
Do you mind if I steal that?"
He said, "No. Go ahead." So I ended up
putting it into the dialogue.
And it ended up being the line that
everybody remembers from the movie.
And I've seen it used many, many times
in all kinds of strange contexts.
I'm sure a lot of people don't even know
that it comes from this movie now.
VERONICA:
You're changing.
Everything about you is changing.
You look bad.
You smell bad.
I've never bathed much.
Those weird hairs that grew out
of your back...
COMMENTARY:
So here's Brundle, the fly-fusion addict...
...still in denial about...
...the dangers
of what's going on with him.
BRUNDLE:
The hairs?
Oh, yeah.
That's a strange thing to do.
Not as strange as the results.
The guy had trouble identifying them.
COMMENTARY:
Still thinking about...
...the upside of fly-ness.
BRUNDLE:
Oh.
-Very good.
-Not human, Seth.
In fact, very likely insect hairs.
That's ridiculous.
Look.
There's more. Look at your face.
COMMENTARY:
And at this point, I suppose it's--
Their relationship is now like
the relationship that people have...
...with drug addicts and alcoholics...
...who are determined to only see
good things about their addictions...
...and not admit that there could
possibly be anything wrong with it.
BRUNDLE:
Does this look like a sick man to you?
No, stop it!
Can a sick man do that?
The deal is off.
I don't need you anymore.
Seth, please, wait. Seth!
Don't come back.
Oh, God...
[CRIES]
COMMENTARY:
Now, this scene, I mean...
...this is really a classic moment...
...in the history of anybody's
individual disease.
That is that you are innocently
looking in the mirror...
...you are innocently cutting
your toenails or taking a shower...
...and you feel something,
you see something...
...and even though it's a small thing,
it's a very, very wrong thing.
And so...
...you know, this has great
reverberations, I think...
...for anybody, healthy or not...
...in terms of...
...the fear of diseases of all kinds.
I mean, if you read any newspaper
or you watch television...
...you're amazed that
anybody's alive at all.
There are so many things
that can attack you.
And...
...most of them aren't fly fusion.
But on a metaphorical level,
on an emotional level...
...this is just a classic scene,
you know.
You find a lump, you find a bump,
you find a lesion...
...you find your fingernail comes off.
So there was certainly
a lot of discussion...
...about The Fly really
being about AIDS.
And I had to say that, of course,
in the era that the movie was made...
...that was certainly front-page news.
But for me,
the movie was just about...
...the normal process of aging.
And, of course,
possibly disease as well.
But it wasn't specifically about AIDS.
That certainly wasn't in my mind.
And I thought that it was really...
...much more about the inevitability
of deterioration and death.
And that that's where the movie
got a lot of its power from...
...was just that it's--
Anybody can relate to it, really.
Despite the fact that...
...the circumstances in the movie
are fantastical and sci-fi and so on...
...the emotional
and very physical reality...
...is absolutely accurate and true.
And what's more, inevitable.
So it's hard to escape
that vibe of The Fly.
That's one of the things that I found
very disturbing when I watched it.
You know, I was surprised that I was
quite shaky after I watched this movie.
It really surprised me.
Normally, it's very hard for me to react
to watching my own movies...
...because I remember
everything that happened...
...on the day that we shot every shot.
And so it's a kind of
a mini-documentary to me...
...about what I was doing that day.
And that makes it very hard
to react to my own movies...
...as though they're movies, basically.
But I did manage to do that
with The Fly somehow...
...even though I was also thinking
about all those other things.
And I found it to be a very, as I say,
profoundly disturbing experience.
And the reason, of course,
is that I'm older now...
...I've experienced more of
the things that I was just anticipating...
...in a kind of precocious understanding
20 years ago when I made this movie.
And so, for me, this movie isn't really
about AIDS. It's about mortality...
...and the way that we deal with it
and try to understand it...
...and the philosophies and emotional
attitudes that we develop towards it.
That's the existentialist in me
speaking here.
I've often said that this movie,
if it were made as a straight drama...
...would never have gotten made,
because it's really quite depressing.
But because it's protected
by the trappings of the genre...
...because it's a sci-fi horror movie,
all of that seems to be okay.
But if you tried to sell somebody
on a movie about two attractive...
...eccentric people who fall in love...
...and then one of them contracts
a hideous, wasting disease...
...and the other one watches
as he deteriorates...
...and then helps him commit suicide at
the end, this is a tough sell for a movie.
This is not something that would
probably get made very easily.
But that is what the plot
of this movie is.
And yet, it doesn't feel quite like that.
Because of the sweetness and
eccentricity of the love story, partly...
...and the attractiveness of it
and of the actors.
And then also because
of the sci-fi underpinnings...
...which are intriguing and provocative
and also fun.
BRUNDLE:
I've been afraid to see you.
Now I'm afraid not to.
Are you at home?
You don't know how right you were.
I've gotten...
...much, much worse.
COMMENTARY:
But you really have to consider...
...how many people...
...have given themselves their own
death sentence in their bathrooms...
...by discovering that thing in the
shower or in the bathtub or in the mirror.
That's where the potency
of those scenes comes from.
VERONICA:
Seth?
I'm here.
BRUNDLE:
Stop!
Seth!
COMMENTARY: And once again,
it was very important to have Seth...
...be articulate about
what was going on with himself.
As people--
Well, we know of many people
who have written books about their--
The diseases that they've been
afflicted with that eventually kill them.
And some of those books are quite
brilliant and illuminating...
...even though they're always depressing
because of the ending.
And so I wanted this to have
some of that feeling.
That we would understand...
...both the intellectual
and emotional twists and turns...
...that he was going through
as he experienced this.
Then of course, what happens is
that the audience then...
...gets to experience it more as well.
It makes it that much more potent
and viscerally affecting.
BRUNDLE: --transmitter pod with
me that first time when I was alone.
COMMENTARY:
This movie won an Oscar...
...for makeup effects.
It's the only movie that I've done...
...that was nominated for an Oscar
of any kind, and it won.
It was quite fun to be there
on that day...
...even though not being personally
nominated myself...
...I was not sitting
on the ground floor...
...but was with my wife
up on the third or fourth floor...
...of the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion.
But it was still fun.
My first time at the Oscars.
BRUNDLE: I'm the offspring
of Brundle and a housefly.
Oh, God. Oh, God, Seth!
You look so pretty.
COMMENTARY:
But it was important for me not to--
Even in scenes like this,
to not lose sight of the fly-ness...
...of what was happening to him...
...that we were heading for a major--
This was all a process,
a gradual transformation...
...that we're kind of forcing the audience
to experience along with Veronica.
And...
But it had to have meaning.
It had to have narrative meaning.
And it had to have some sense
and cohesion of the kind...
...that I didn't find in
the original movie of The Fly.
I wanted it to all have
a weird scientific logic...
...underneath
the horrible emotional logic.
This. So it's scenes like that.
Knowing how a fly works,
how a fly digests its food...
...how completely different insects
are from humans...
...and yet somehow connected.
BRUNDLE:
Oh.
That's disgusting.
COMMENTARY:
Oh, this is kind of the operatic version...
...of anybody's disease, basically.
BRUNDLE:
My...
...ear. No!
COMMENTARY: This moment, I mean,
this is where the audience screamed.
And I think this is where
we had a lot of people fainting...
...was when Geena, or Veronica,
actually hugs Seth...
...in this condition, and puts her face
up to where his ear used to be.
That really got a lot of screams,
I have to say.
And in a way, it was unexpected,
but wonderful.
VERONICA:
That's your advice?
It could be contagious.
It could become an epidemic.
COMMENTARY:
And I really liked what happened here...
...was that
I've deliberately cut down...
...the human frames of reference
that all the characters have.
I mean, there are no mothers, brothers,
sisters, families, relatives.
So Veronica has to go back
to her old boyfriend for support...
...who's also, of course, her employer.
But it is really a triangle.
The movie really is a triangle.
And in that sense, it's very schematic.
Of course, people don't only know
two other people...
...especially if they're normal people
out in the world, working.
STATHIS:
Look, how about this?
COMMENTARY:
But I wanted her to be forced...
...to go back to Stathis...
...because of the sparks that there were
between them...
...and then because
of the emotional motivation...
...he would have
to risk his life to help her.
Not to mention that...
...he had mixed feelings,
of course, about...
...the deterioration of his great rival
for Veronica's love.
At one point, I think--
We did actually shoot a scene...
...that would end the movie
where she was living with Stathis...
...having married him,
got out of bed with him.
Audiences really hated that, and I had
to say I didn't like it very much myself.
They just didn't wanna see that.
But you never know.
That might have been
where Veronica ended up.
VERONICA:
Seth?
BRUNDLE:
No, no, no. Up here.
COMMENTARY:
Now, here is something that I'm sure...
...would've been done completely
by computer today...
...but was a completely physical effect.
It required building
a huge Ferris wheel.
The room was a Ferris wheel
that rotated.
So that when the camera
was upside down...
...and as Brundle crawls down the walls,
the set is rotating.
So he's really on the floor.
You know, it's gravity.
It's just gravity is doing the whole trick.
But...
...the set is revolving
as we shoot that shot.
And Mark Irwin, my director
of photography for this movie...
...worked out
a very ingenious system...
...for lighting inside that Ferris wheel,
which involved...
...bouncing light off mirrors and so on,
because there wasn't much throw.
There wasn't much distance
that you could get from...
From the set and from the actor,
in order to light it properly.
So there was a whole system of mirrors
and lighting through mirrors.
And all of that rotated with the set.
And it was a huge set.
It was quite an engineering feat to build
with the bearings that it had and so on.
I remember watching Ingmar Bergman's
film Hour of the Wolf...
...which had a scene where someone
is so grief-stricken, he walks up a wall.
But that was done very simply,
with no camera movement...
...and not following a moving actor.
So it was really a question of...
...building a floor
that looked like a ceiling...
...and shooting down onto it.
I remember looking at that movie,
though. A brilliant movie.
I'm a big Bergman fan.
Looking to it for guidance,
but it was done very starkly.
And it was very effective,
but it wouldn't have worked...
...for what we needed in this movie.
BRUNDLE:
How does Brundlefly eat?
He found out the hard way...
COMMENTARY: We actually looked at
a Fred Astaire movie...
...I think it was called
Royal Wedding...
...in which he dances up from the floor
to the wall to the ceiling.
And they used a revolving set then
in that movie.
We really just replicated
some very old technology for that one.
BRUNDLE:
He regurgitates on his food.
It liquefies.
And then he sucks it back up.
Ready for a demonstration, kids?
Here it goes.
[BRUNDLE REGURGITATES]
Oh, my God.
My God!
[DOOR OPENS]
COMMENTARY:
And once again, the whole idea...
...of documenting your life...
...no matter how hideous...
...in fact, the more hideous the moment,
the more you wanna document it.
And in a way,
it takes you out of your life.
It makes it a movie.
It makes it not be real.
And I think that's why people
have the impulse...
...to document their own lives now.
Even their worst moments.
Or especially their worst moments.
VERONICA:
I'm pregnant.
Oh, no.
COMMENTARY:
Now, here we're into territory...
...that there was not...
...in the original movie of The Fly,
of course, and the short story.
But it's just a natural evolution...
...of a sexual relationship
and a love affair.
VERONICA:
I just...
I don't know.
COMMENTARY:
Gradually, Toronto has become...
...just a series of sets and locations...
...that are in my movies, to me.
Every time I turn a corner,
it's another place that I've shot...
...some scenes in a movie.
And I like that, actually.
VERONICA: Why am I losing it?
-It's better this way. You'll see.
It's the best thing that could happen.
COMMENTARY:
It's true I have a cameo in this scene...
...and it wasn't something
that I wanted.
And it's not something that I do.
I always prefer to get
better actors than me in my movies.
But there I am, with those very hideous
'80s glasses that were so popular.
And Geena asked me to do this role...
...because she just felt
she wanted me there.
If anybody was gonna be in that position
when she was up in the stirrups...
...she would rather it be her director.
So I said I would do it,
knowing that, of course...
...my face would be covered, and then
I could get somebody to dub my lines...
...if I wasn't happy
with my performance.
But I thought I did well enough,
so I left them in.
But those glasses. Oh, well.
Aesthetics change, don't they?
VERONICA:
No!
[VERONICA SCREAMING]
COMMENTARY: Once again, of course,
an incredibly potent nightmare.
The idea that you'll give birth
to something monstrous.
Whether you're an artist or a human
or a woman who is of childbearing age...
...this is a-- There's a lot
of very potent fears...
...touched on in this movie.
And that's really the strength
of the horror film.
That is the strength of the genre,
that it doesn't...
It cuts right to the chase, as they say.
It really deals with primal fears
very directly.
And that's obviously part
of the enduring popularity...
...of horror tales
that have always existed.
That it's...
If you can somehow have something
be even worse than what's in your life...
...it's somehow comforting.
Going further than even
your worst nightmare.
And that's what good horror films
give you.
And that's what The Fly
gave a lot of people as well.
Here's why I wanted
voice recognition...
...and why speech was so important.
Because...
...the idea that Brundle
should lose his voice...
...should lose his ability to articulate...
...10 me was a major moment
of horror and fear.
Which if you play it the way
the original was structured...
...wouldn't have ever been an issue.
One moment he can speak,
and the next minute he can't.
And that was it.
I wanted this also to be part...
...of the transition.
The ongoing deterioration.
And the idea of a little personal museum
of your former body parts...
...I think is even more relevant
these days...
...when so many people
do have former body parts...
...or are swapping body parts
with other people.
BRUNDLE:
Artifacts of a bygone era.
COMMENTARY:
It seems to be part...
...of the strange physical future
of the human race.
We'll all have these little museums
for ourselves...
...if we don't already.
BRUNDLE:
You've missed some good moments.
COMMENTARY:
Quite a few actors were approached...
...about playing this role...
...and most of them who said no
were afraid of the rubber.
They were afraid of the makeup.
They were afraid that
they would not be able...
...to act through the rubber,
that they would be lost.
And Jeff was totally not afraid.
On the contrary,
he was looking forward to it.
It was not even just a challenge,
it was something that he was...
He felt he could use,
and he wasn't afraid of it.
And that, you can see,
this would be the scene...
...that an actor would
either be intimidated...
...by what he had to wear, or not.
And Jeff, of course,
obviously was not.
And it required a lot of hours
in the makeup chair too.
I mean, it's quite a torturous
kind of thing to go through.
Starting very early in the morning, and
then starting five hours before that...
...in order to have
your makeup put on.
And being very uncomfortable
all the while.
I think Geena used to sing to Jeff...
...and read to him
while he was having his makeup put on.
BRUNDLE:
--and never come back here.
Have you heard of insect politics?
Neither have I.
COMMENTARY:
The insect-politics speech...
...has become somewhat famous
as well.
It's just my observation as, as I say,
a junior entomologist from an early age.
I was very fascinated by insect societies
like the kind that ants have.
There is a division of labor,
and they do attack...
...other ant colonies
and run off with slaves.
And they do have slaves,
and they do have...
...what they call ant cows.
They milk aphids for their honey.
So they have a very advanced
kind of social structure.
But they are still very, very much
not human...
...and that's really what
I was trying to get at with this speech.
And once again, Brundle is aware of it.
He's aware of what is happening to him,
and he can articulate it.
And to me, that makes it more poignant
and more tragic...
...and also more emotionally effective
and involving for the audience.
BRUNDLE:
--and the insect is awake.
No, Seth.
I'm saying...
...I'll hurt you if you stay.
[GROANING]
COMMENTARY:
Now, who knows how this...
...would have been done
in the modern era.
You know, certainly, there's a man
in a rubber suit playing the scene.
And it's obvious.
Of course, there are many ways
to do that now...
...where you might have
the actor acting...
...a completely
computer-generated character.
Although, doing the acting himself...
...would have been
more extreme and more effective...
...in the sense of body shape that
an actual human body could not have.
But there's a sort of an immediacy
and a physicality and a realness...
...to the man-in-the-rubber-suit
routine...
...that's very effective as well.
So I suppose it might, you know,
look very, hm, tacky...
...and a few other things
to a modern audience.
But at the same time...
...there's an immediacy
and a physical presence...
...that you don't get with CGI.
And I wonder in about 20 years' time
how something like this...
...will compare with the way
CGI looks to a future audience.
Because CGI also has its drawbacks...
...and it, too, might look quite tacky
and primitive in 20 years...
...or even fewer years than that.
DOCTOR:
Well, okay, what's the story?
COMMENTARY: This actor, Les Carlson,
I've worked with him in many movies...
...Videodrome in particular.
He's just a favorite Canadian actor
of mine I love to work with.
He plays Barry Convex,
the bad guy, in Videodrome.
STATHIS:
Please.
Is it your child?
No.
It's the child of a man
who is deformed.
I don't mean to interfere...
...but I detect a certain
uncertainty here.
There are tests we can do
to determine whether--
I don't want tests.
Tests can't guarantee anything.
The baby could start off normal,
then become...
I want an abortion.
I'll do it myself if I have to.
If you'll slip into that,
we'll be on our way in no time.
COMMENTARY: Once again,
this is another hot button, I suppose...
...and it's gotten hotter
since we made this movie.
That is, the idea of abortion,
and aborting a fetus...
...that might or might not be
monstrous or deformed...
...or defective in some way or other.
I was operating one of the cameras...
...that shot that jumping-through-
the-glass-blocks moment.
I don't normally like to operate...
...because you start to worry more about
your framing and so on...
...than the dramatic things
that are going on.
But I think we ran out of operators
at that point...
...So I operated one of the cameras.
That was a set
that we were just looking at...
...but this is really the rooftop
of the Bishop Strachan School...
...which is really around the corner
from my house.
A school where two
of my daughters attended.
Great rooftop.
BRUNDLE:
--want to kill Brundle?
The baby might be all that's left
of the real me.
COMMENTARY:
Once again, this is a scene...
...that could have been done in a studio
with green screen and so on...
...but we were actually up there
on that roof.
VERONICA:
I'm afraid.
Please, have the baby.
I can't.
COMMENTARY:
The scenes like this are really, I found...
...very, very, very
emotionally wrenching, I have to say.
And I guess the argument for rubber
would be best with that scene.
You know, you see an actual face
and an actual person acting.
You know it's not drawn
and it's not drawn by computer.
That's a real person there.
And the emotion
really does come through.
Now we have the good Stathis,
you see?
He's heroic,
and he's come to rescue his woman.
And I think it was implicit all the time.
You really suddenly realize...
...that he wasn't really
the bad guy after all.
He was another part of a real triangle.
But, of course, he's out of his depth.
This shotgun, of course,
is not a combat shotgun.
It's really for skeet shooting
or bird shooting.
It's not really...
It's a kind of an effete,
rather pretty, elegant gun.
Not good for fly hunting, really.
Even props
are expressive of character.
And getting the design
of the props right is a real art.
Once again, a computer
has to make it perfectly clear.
[SCREECHES]
Jesus!
Ah!
COMMENTARY:
We did have a complete...
...Brundlefly puppet...
...for those moments of vomiting
of fly fluid.
You'll see him again.
And this is him.
A puppet being operated
by about 20 guys under the floor...
...as they usually do.
There's Jeff.
VERONICA:
No, don't. Don't, please.
Please.
COMMENTARY:
A lot of literary reverberations.
You know, you've certainly got
Beauty and the Beast happening here.
A lot of force,
but ultimately behind the story...
...in terms of mythology and archetype,
I suppose.
We're in the rotating set again
with this shot.
BRUNDLE:
Help me.
Help me be human.
How?
Well...
COMMENTARY:
And once again...
...like an old couple
who can't really experience anything...
...unless they share it
with each other...
...Brundle just simply wants to share.
And of course, there's a kind of a
Frankenstein reverb there as well.
The idea that Frankenstein
wants a monster wife.
BRUNDLE:
Together.
No...
We'll be the ultimate family.
A family of three,
joined together in one body.
COMMENTARY:
Jeff had to learn to speak...
...with various kinds
of prosthetic teeth.
He had to have a speech therapist
work with him.
Of course, now he stops talking.
But you see how late in the movie
the talking is over.
Because there's not much
of the movie left to go...
...80 it was all right for him
to lose it, finally...
...for his final transformation.
But yes, he had to learn how
to continue to speak...
...with various prosthetic teeth,
which were a part of his transformation.
And develop the sort of twitching,
the fly twitching...
...without it being too much,
and without it being over-the-top.
VERONICA:
Oh, God, please!
COMMENTARY: And, of course,
this is a full-sized puppet.
Huge.
And beautifully operated.
And so is this.
These are things that I think now
would definitely be done CGI...
...and they would have
more fluidity and so on.
But they might not quite have
the physical presence.
So you gain things
and you lose things.
If you've watched an insect...
...you know that they do move
like little puppets.
I mean, they-- There can be a kind of
puppetlike motion to both rodents...
...like rats and squirrels, and insects.
So that was very possible
to replicate that...
...with the motion that you see there
with this puppet.
Now, this fly-fusion creature...
...definitely does not have
the eyes of an insect.
Maybe if I'm the kid in the audience,
this is what I'm gonna complain about.
But I wanted it, of course, to have...
...some human expressiveness
for the emotion.
And I guess you could justify it
by saying:
"Well, it got Brundle's eyes, even if
it didn't get the rest of his body."
So I went for emotional eyes
on this creature.
I thought they were very important...
...and, of course, you'll see soon
why we needed them.
They're kind of a big version
of Jeff's eyes...
...with a little bit of a green tint
to give you the insect aspect.
But insect eyes are not expressive, and
I really needed expressiveness now...
...because we no longer had
the articulation.
He could no longer speak, of course.
So the eyes were all that was left.
Because Brundle, of course...
...has to make it clear
that he wants to die.
And he can't say it.
So he has to use his eyes.
There were many possible codas
that we thought of for the movie...
...that dealt with Veronica giving birth.
Or not giving birth. Giving birth
to a perfectly healthy baby...
...giving birth to a butterfly baby,
all kinds of--
Or maybe that was a dream.
But we found that the ending
was so shattering for the audience...
...that they-- Nothing really worked.
I mean, there was really--
They didn't really wanna hear or see
anything after this.
And it's funny, because I had
the same structural situation...
...on The Dead Zone,
which ends just like this.
I mean, it's the same ending
as The Dead Zone, basically.
Although in this case, the woman
actually does the mercy killing.
There were many attempts to--
Or several attempts
on The Dead Zone also...
...to have a kind of coda that dealt
with the characters who were left...
...after the Chris Walken character dies
in The Dead Zone.
I hope I haven't spoiled it for you
if you haven't seen it.
But none of them worked...
...and it just seemed better to just
get out when the movie was over...
...rather than try to deal with something
that just wasn't gonna work.
So it occurred to me...
...when we were deciding what to do
about the ending here...
...that it would probably be best to just
do what we did with The Dead Zone...
...which was to leave it
with the death of the main character...
...and that was the end of the movie.
The question of technology and science
and morality and ethics...
...is often raised in my movies.
And there has been, of course,
the kind of...
The Romantic concept of going too far.
That you cannot assault the gods.
If you fly too close to the sun...
...the wax
holding your wings together melts...
...and you plunge to your doom.
I don't really believe in destiny per se.
But I think that it is innate in our nature
to constantly change everything...
...to question everything,
to try to understand everything.
And it will inevitably create
good and bad.
And I don't think
there's any stopping it.
And, of course, now that we've sort of
dived into the plasma pool, literally...
...that we are dealing with DNA,
and the double helix...
...and the actual structure of life itself
and the human body...
...and the question of
human consciousness and so on...
...it's a Pandora's box,
in the sense that it has been opened...
...and it will not be closed.
There's no question.
So I think we have to just accept
that that is what our destiny is...
...to do all those things. To change
everything. To try to control everything.
And also to fail at it
in terms of the big picture.
I think it's a constant struggling,
a constant striving.
And it's true that
characters in my movies who do that...
...often come to terrible ends...
...but that has more, I think,
to do with the nature of drama...
...than it does
with the nature of philosophy.
It has to do with the fact that...
...as George Bernard Shaw said,
"Conflict is the essence of drama.”
So if you have someone
who comes up with a great invention...
...or a great cure for a disease...
...and it works
and that's the end of it...
...then it's not much of a drama.
So it's much more
interesting dramatically...
...and it's also more illuminating,
when things go wrong.
It's when things go wrong
that you understand...
...the nature of what happens
when things go right.
So I'm not really trying to promote
a conservative approach to science...
...or to art at all.
And I think you can see, too...
...that even with what Brundle
undergoes in this movie...
...there is an exhilaration.
There is an incredible experience
that he has.
And though he ends up dying...
...one can say,
"Well, we all end up dying...
...and perhaps it's more interesting,
more exciting...
...more thrilling, a better way to live...
...to have gone through
an amazing transformation...
...an amazing adventure in your life."
To die young,
but to die young in an amazing way...
...having had a terrifically exciting
or provocative life.
It's a tossup, you know.
And I think that that flip of the coin...
...is where we are at as humans.
[ENGLISH SDH]